Guide to the Papers of Frances Patai ALBA.131
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Frances Patai Papers
1937-1998, (Bulk 1989-1997)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Patai, Frances
ALBA.131
5 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
Frances Patai was an educator, writer, historian and feminist activist. Born in New York in 1930 she earned her bachelors and masters degrees at the City College of New York in the 1950s and taught English and communication courses throughout the City University of New York (CUNY) system. Throughout her career Patai was concerned with the rights and status of women, and in the last decade of her life she devoted her efforts to researching and writing a book on women medical personnel who volunteered during the Spanish Civil War. Patai died in 1998 before she could bring her project to fruition. She was 67 years old. The Patai Papers consist predominantly of research materials she gathered and drafts she produced during the course of her work on her unpublished book, Heroines of the Good Fight: U.S. Women Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War including articles, clippings, and notes.
Provenance
This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. The Patai Papers were donated by Frances Patai in 1998.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Frances Patai was born in New York City's Lower East Side in 1930. As a teenager, Patai performed in Jewish resorts in the Catskills as an actress and dancer. In her twenties she attended classes at City College of New York earning her bachelor's degree in 1955 and her MA in 1957. Beginning in the 1970s she served as an English and communications instructor at various institutions in the City University of New York (CUNY) system including long-term appointments at John Jay and the Borough of Manhattan Community Colleges.
Throughout her career Patai was concerned with the rights and status of women, addressing in a series of essays and articles issues related to rape, pornography, and abuse. During the 1980s she worked with the feminist organization Woman Against Pornography, serving as spokesperson and organizing their annual WAP Awards, an event that promoted the non-sexist representation of women in advertising. In later life Patai turned her attention to the anti-fascist movements of the 1930s, and began to investigate the history of American volunteers who joined the Republican forces to fight against Franco's army during the Spanish Civil War. Patai focused her attention on the participation of American women volunteers in the Spanish Civil War devoting her efforts to researching and writing a book on the contributions of nurses. Through her friendship with Fredericka Martin - a nurse with the Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy who accrued extensive biographical material on her former colleagues - Patai gained access to unique primary materials. Patai died in 1998 before she could bring her project to fruition. She was 67 years old. Shortly before her death, Patai established an endowment to the City College Center for Worker Education to fund annual courses and lectures on the Nazi Holocaust.
Sources:
Rimmel, Leslie, "Frances (Francesca) Patai, 1930-1998," Off Our Backs(Washington), April 1998.
Leberstein, Stephen, "Eloquence of Former Chancellor Sparks Major CCNY Bequest," CUNY Matters, Spring 1998.
Scope and Content Note
The Frances Patai Papers consist predominantly of research materials she gathered and the drafts she produced during the course of her work on her unpublished book, Heroines of the Good Fight: U.S. Women Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War including articles, clippings, and notes. The collection is arranged in three series.
Series I: biographical files of nurses and other women personnel who served during the Spanish Civil War. These contain recollections and firsthand accounts of the wartime medical facilities and the conditions in Spain during the conflict.
Series II: published and unpublished materials by Patai, including drafts of her book, articles about the women in the International Brigades, conference papers and proposals, and miscellaneous writings on pornography and sexual abuse.
Series III: This series is made up of subject files. Included here are notes, excerpt from publications, and research materials on general topics, organizations, and individuals as well as biographical material on Patai. Notable among these files are copies of Jirku Gusti's, "We Fight Death," and Sandor Voros' unpublished manuscript on hospitals and medical services.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series.
Organized into three series
Missing Title
I. Biographical Files
II. Writings
III. Subject Files
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Photographs were separated from Patai's manuscript materials in the course of processing. For further information related to the scope and contents of her photograph collection see, The Frances Patai Photographs, ALBA Photo, 131.
Audio tapes from the Patai Papers have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Research (document genres).; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Articles.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Drafts (documents); Biography files.; Correspondence.; Americans |z Spain |x History |y 20th century.; Patai, Frances; Voros, Sandor.; Martin, Fredericka I.; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Jirku, Gusti.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; City University of New York; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy
- Series I: Biographical Files
  - Alcade, Carmen, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Andell, Evelyn, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bell, Hilda (Roberts), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brisker, Luba, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bruzzichesi, Ava, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chadwick, Selma, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Davidow, Ruth, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - DeVries, Lini (Fuhr), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Duncan, Cleo, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dyer, Edith, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Edwards, Thyra, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Erickson, Thelma (Byrne), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Esther, Hon (Brown), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ferwerda, Ena (Andry), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fontaine, Dorothy (Mardfin), undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Foy, Mable (Levin), undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Freed, Rose, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Freedman, Helen (Feinberg), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Galleani, Gerumina, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Goldblatt, Sana, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Golden, Irene (Spiegel), undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Golub, Fannie, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Greenspan, Celia (Seborer), undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Grunsky, Eugenia, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Harris, Ray (Marantz), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hershkowitz, Honey, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hutchins, Evelyn (Rahman), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Jensky, Toby, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Jirku, Gusti (Stridsberg), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Kee, Salaria (a.k.a. Salaria Kea, later O'Reilly), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Kyle, Constance (Lamb), undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Leight, Clara, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Levine, May (Hartzman), undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Martin, Fredericka, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Malbin, Virginia (Social Worker), undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Merims, Sonia (Kolkin), undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Merriman, Marion (Wachtel), undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Montseny, Federica, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - North, Helen (Green), undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Novac, Alba (Ryan), undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Perez, Leonor, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Pike, Florence, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Plotkin, Mary (Torrance), undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Rackley, Mildred (Simon), undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Rader, Mary (Garrity), undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Rolfe, Mary, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Romer, Edna (Drabkin), undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Schulman, Rebecca (Durem), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Shuldiner, Anna (Goldman), undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Silverstein, Esther (Blanc), undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Taft, Anne (Muldaven), undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Temple, Leonora, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Vanzant, Frances Dr., undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Wacksman, Rose (Sorkin), undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Wagnon, Alice (Martin), undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Wilkes, Harry, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Williams, Helen, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Wilson, Ruth (Epstein), undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Weissman, Helene, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Series II: Writings
  - Book Reviews: Memories of Resistance by Shirley Mangini and Defying Male Civilization by Mary Nash, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Dolores Ibarruri, 'La Pasionaria' (1895-1998)... (Article), 1997-02-06 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Heroines, Humanitarians, Anti-Fascists: US Women Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War, 1994-01-11 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Heroines of the Good Fight: Book Proposal, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Heroines of the Good Fight: Introduction (2 versions), undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Heroines of the Good Fight: Part I, Chapter 1, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Heroines of the Good Fight: Part I, Chapter 2, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Heroines of the Good Fight: Sources Used and Methodology, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Heroines of the Good Fight: Table of Contents (2 versions), undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Heroines of the Good Fight: Testimonies of U.S. Volunteer Nurses in the Spanish Civil War (different versions), undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Heroines of the Good Fight: U.S. Women Medical Service Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War (2 versions), undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Humanitarian Work as Anti-Fascist Political Action (conference paper and other versions), undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - I'm a Forever Anti-Fascist: Voices of US Women Medical Service Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War (Article based on oral histories), undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Medical Bureau History: Outline and Drafts, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Mujeres voluntarias estadounidenses en la guerra civil espanola... (Article in Spanish), 1996-03 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - New York City Labor Chorus: Singing International Solidarity (Article), 1997-04-21 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - 1936 International Anti-Fascists Return to Spain for 1996 Homage (Article), 1996-11 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Power, Paychecks, Protest, Pain in the Real World of 'Women's Work' (Conference Paper Proposal), 1994-10 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Prostitution: Miscellaneous Writings, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Twentieth Century Judiths: US Women Anti-Fascist Volunteers... (Conference Paper Proposal), 1996-06 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - With Liberty and Justice for Whom? (Letter to editor of NY Times), 1995-05-23 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Untitled Article on U.S. Women Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Series III: Subject Files
  - Ambulances, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - American Medical Bureau: Accounts, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - American Medical Bureau: History, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - American Medical Bureau: Miscellany from F. Martin, 1937-1986 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Fascist (?) Leaflet: Welcome to the International Brigade, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Fisher, Ruth and Harry, undated, 1938, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Franco's 'Mein Kampf' (Spanish Information Bureau), 1939 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Garcia Lorca, Federico, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Gonshak, Sam, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Holman, Portia: "Hospital in Spain", 1937 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Hornstein, Claire Hartford, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Jewish Volunteers, 1938, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Jirku, Gusti: We Fight Death (photocopies), ca.1937 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Kutnick, Lee (Executive Secretary, Friends of ALBA), 1992 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Martin, Fredericka: "The American Indian" (inscribed to F. Patai), Spring 1950 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Medical Aid: General, 1938-1941 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Nurses: General, 1937-1977 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Palmer, Nettie and Len Fox, "Australians in Spain", 1948 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Patai, Frances: Biographical, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Patai, Frances: Book Project, Miscellaneous Notes and Forms, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Patai Fund: CUNY, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Poder y Libertad: Special Women's Issue (articles by Patai and Martin), 1989 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Radio Broadcasts: Transcripts from New York Public Library and Columbia University, 1937-1938 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Redondo, Carmen (Rescued by U.S. Nurses) and Jose Luis, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Relief Ship, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Soccoro, Rojo, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Social Workers: Aid to Spain, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Spain: Veterans' Visit, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Voros, Sandor: Unpublished Manuscript on Hospitals and Medical Services in Spain, ca.1937 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Women in the Spanish Civil War: Miscellaneous Papers and Articles, 1936-1996 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Women Volunteers: From F. Martin, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)